Guide to the Roger W. Moss Collection of Manuscript, Original Art and Printed Material by and about Richard Shirley Smith
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
Roger W. Moss Collection of Manuscript, Original Art and Printed Material by and about Richard Shirley Smith
1961-2011
MSS.17
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
15
The collection comprises manuscripts, original art and printed material by and about Richard Shirley Smith, collected by Roger W. Moss.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Roger W. Moss, 2011
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into six series: I. Books and Articles on Richard Shirley Smith; II. Publications Designed or Illustrated by Richard Shirley Smith; III. Engraved and Drawn Bookplates by Richard Shirley Smith; IV. Engravings by Richard Shirley Smith; V. Ephemera; VI. Correspondence. Arrangement follows, to the extent possible, that of the checklist by Roger W. Moss.
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises manuscripts, original art and printed material by and about Richard Shirley Smith, collected by Roger W. Moss. A description of the collection is provided in the forward to Moss's checklist, Richard Shirley Smith: illustrated books, engravings and bookplates: annotated checklist, Roger W. Moss Collection (Marlborough, England: Libanus Press, 2010):
This checklist of Richard Shirley Smith's illustrated books, engravings and bookplates is intended to compliment lain Bain's Wood Engravings of Richard Shirley Smith (Cambridge, 1994), Shirley Smith's Paintings & Collages (London, 2002), and Brian North Lee's Bookplates by Richard Shirley Smith (Fleece Press, 2005). It also documents my own collection begun after I commissioned Shirley Smith to produce a millennium year ex libris for books acquired by an endowment in my name at The Athenaeum of Philadelphia. Since I could never hope to own more than a few of his paintings and none of his trompe l'oeil murals--many of which are in privately-owned country houses--I focused on the books he has illustrated over the past half century. Eventually I added original strikes of virtually all the engravings and bookplates as well, including items unrecorded by Iain Bain and Brian North Lee. From the beginning the collection was destined for an appropriate institution in the United States where the work of this versatile artist is not as well known as it should be. In England collections of Shirley Smith's engravings already exist at the Ashmolean Museum, Oxford and also in London at the British Museum and the Victoria & Albert Museum. The Bodleian Library have asked to receive his main archive.
Richard Shirley Smith was born in London (1935) and educated at Harrow and the Slade School of Fine Art. After a year and a half of further study in Rome, he returned to England in 1962 to support his young family as a freelance graphic designer for commercial publishers. Richard was not encouraging when I began to collect these early books, preferring that I concentrate on the finely printed limited editions of his mature work. But these early commissions paid the bills and gave him practical experience in book design and publishing. Most were for dust jackets, but occasionally he was asked to illustrate an entire book. He produced fifty drawings for Wilfrid Blunt's Of Flowers & A Village (Hamish Hamilton, 1963), and for each of the nine biographies of musicians by Percy M. Young published by Ernest Benn he provided at least a dozen drawings that ranged from portraits to landscapes and architecture. Fortunately for his later career, some publishers recognized the exceptional quality of his wood engravings, which were far more tedious and time consuming to produce than the mono-types and drawings typically commissioned. Shirley Smith's engraved portrait of Sir Thomas More set against a detailed London background, for example, was commissioned by Burns & Oates and used for several of Ernest Edwin Reynolds's books published in both England and the United States.
It was the art directors at Faber and Faber who particularly favoured Shirley Smith's wood engravings. Ten of these appeared in their edition of Douglas Bartrum's The Gourmet's Garden (1964) and another ten in Elizabeth Clarke's The Darkening Green (1964). The discipline of working against a publisher's deadline for a set of ten original engravings would be valuable experience in the future.
Often a catalogue raisonné--or even a simple, chronological checklist such as this one--illuminates important turning points in an artist's career. For Richard Shirley Smith, 1967 stands out. In that year, seventeen of his wood engravings dating from his studies in Rome were featured by The Golden Head Press in a slim volume of Joyce Finzi's poetry; The Folio Society published thirty of his wood engravings commissioned for their limited edition of Sir Roger de Coverly; and in New York, Macmillan released Memoirs of a London Doll illustrated with fifteen commissioned wood engravings.
The 1967 projects prompted the typographical advisor and historian John Dreyfus (1918-2002), who was an agent for the Limited Editions Club in the United States, to suggest Shirley Smith as the illustrator for Stephen Spender's selection of Shelley's poems which was published in 1971. For this commission he executed forty-six wood engravings. Of this project Richard wrote: 'I think ... this was my "masterpiece" as regards engraving' and John Dreyfus would later remark, Shirley Smith 'was able to render intricate details of architecture, landscape, seascape, flora, fauna and the human face--all with equal mastery and with astonishing control of perspective and the lighting of the different planes.' Laurence Whistler, brother of Rex Whistler, and an artist who recognized genius when he encountered it, wrote 'here is an artist whose scope is not narrow. With equal skill he handles the charming simplicities of doll's house furniture, portraits, houses, food, insects, animals, flowers--and scenes of imagination. In the end it is the last-named that catch and hold the attention. He seems to have discovered his true gift while interpreting, or simply responding to, poetry.'
Shirley Smith had left behind his journeyman work as an engraver and illustrator for commercial publishers. Henceforth he would be in demand by The Folio Society, Oxford University Press, and private press publishers such as Libanus, Rocket, Fleece, and Gruffyground which featured his engravings, line drawings, and paintings in finely bound, limited and signed editions, including such publications as Hugh Shankland's Messer Pietro Mio (1985). Concurrently, several well publicized exhibitions such as his fiftieth birthday retrospective at the Ashmolean Museum and the Royal Institute of British Architects, and several books and articles that are listed in the first section of this checklist have helped to create a steady demand for his easel paintings, murals and fine and limited edition book illustrations.
Since that modest commission to design my book plate, Richard Shirley Smith and I have developed a cordial trans-Atlantic friendship that has given me considerable pleasure. Without his cooperation and encouragement neither the collection nor this publication would have been possible. Roger W. Moss, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.
- Books and Articles on Richard Shirley Smith, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Descriptions in this series are copied, with minor changes, from the Roger W. Moss annotated checklist (with the author's kind permission), reproducing the item enumeration and descriptive conventions used in the checklist. Formatting is modified.
  For each item, a parallel record is included the Yale University Library catalog, and links to the records are provided herewith; the catalog records describe the material according to standard library cataloging conventions.
  For each item, a parallel record is included the Yale University Library catalog, and links to those records are provided herewith; these records describe the material according to standard library cataloging conventions.
  - Prospect: The Schweppes Book of the New Generation. London: Hutchinson, 1962., Bannister, Roger; Pp. [1-14], 15-248; 235 x 165 mm (Volume Moss no. 1)
    Set in Bembo type and printed by The Anchor Press, Ltd., Tiptree, Essex, on a special smooth wove paper; colour plates printed by L. Van Leer & Company, Netherlands. Pages 193-197 devoted to Richard Shirley Smith with reproductions of five wood engravings [Bain nos. 28-32]. Bound in olive-brown book cloth with dust jacket designed by David Gentleman.
    Inclusion in Roger Bannister's Prospect was Shirley Smith's first national recognition as an emerging artist of talent.
    A record for this item is also available in the Yale University Library Catalog.
  - "Bookplate Designs by Richard Shirley Smith." The Private Library 10 (Summer, 1977)., Lee, Brian North; Pp. 84-93; 214 x 138 mm (Volume Moss no. 2)
    With reproductions of six bookplates: Timothy Harman [1962, Bain no. 33, North Lee no. 3], Jacob Rothschild [1973, Bain no. 215, North Lee no. 9], John Retallack [1974, Bain no. 232, North Lee no.11], James Ley Wilson [1974, Bain no. 231, North Lee no. 10], Michael J. Mitchell [1975, Bain no. 236, North Lee no. 13], and Sir George Taylor [1974, Bain no. 233, North Lee no. 12] and four engraved labels: ASHMANSWORTH/ NR NEWBURY * BERKS * [c.1962, for Joyce Finzi, not in Bain], NIGEL FINZI [c.1962, not in Bain], DR ALEC HAY/ 9 WOODSTOCK ROAD/BEDFORD PARK/LONDON .W.4 [c. 1962, not in Bain], and PAX for Valentine Ackland [1962, Bain no. 35]. Sewn soft cover.
    The British bookplate scholar Brian North Lee (1936-2007) became aware of Richard Shirley Smith's engraved bookplates in the early 1970s and his several publications on Shirley Smith spanning nearly twenty years (here listed together in chronological order) brought that branch of his art to the attention of an international audience.
  - Richard Shirley Smith und Seine Holzstich–ExLibris, Österreichsches Jahrbuck für ExLibris und Gebrauchsgraphik Jahrgang 1981–1983. Vienna, 1983., Lee, Brian North; Pp. [1-4] 5-151 [152]; 295 x 218 mm (Volume Moss no. 3)
    Article on pages 74-79 with reproductions of five bookplates: Michael Riviere [1978, Bain no. 241, North Lee no. 14], Auberon Waugh [1978, Bain no. 242, North Lee no. 15], Amanda Karen Petford [1979, Bain no. 244, North Lee no. 17], P. & D. Colnaghi [1980, Bain no. 246, North Lee no. 18], and Adrian Sassoon [1980, Bain no. 248, North Lee no. 20]. Several bookplates by other artists are tipped in. Sewn soft binding. North Lee's copy with his ex libris.
  - Richard Shirley Smith Fiftieth Birthday Retrospective Exhibition. Ashmolean Museum, Oxford, and Royal Institute of British Architects Heinz Gallery, London W1. Sponsored by the Landseer Property Corporation. Privately printed, 1985., Lee, Brian North; Pp. [i-ii] [1-5] 6-55 [56-58]; 245 x 187 mm (Volume Moss no. 4)
    Includes essays by Henry Ford on Shirley Smith's paintings, collages & murals; a retrospective catalogue; Shirley Smith as a wood engraver by Brian North Lee; a catalogue of engravings, 1960-1984; and a chronology. Sewn soft binding.
  - "Richard Shirley Smith" in Artur Mário da Mota Miranda, Encyclopaedia Bio-Bibliographical of the Art of the Contemporary Ex-Libris. Portugal: Editorial Franciscana, 1986., Lee, Brian North; Pp. [1-8] 9-191 [192]; 265 x 210 mm (Volume Moss no. 5)
    Edition limited to 500 numbered copies of which this is no. 41. Article appears on pages 159-174 with photograph and reproductions of seventeen bookplates. Also includes a 'Checklist of Ex-Libris by Richard Shirley Smith' with descriptions of thirty-three bookplates through 1984. Bound in red book cloth. Shirley Smith's copy with his studio ex libris.
  - "Richard Shirley Smith." Ex Libris: Rivista Italiana di Xilografia Ex Libris e Piccola Grafica. Milan, 1987., Lee, Brian North; Pp. 94-97; 275 x 210 mm (Volume Moss no. 6)
    Article appears on pages 94-97 with reproductions of eight bookplates: John Loch [1983, Bain no. 254, North Lee no. 23], Iain Bain [1983, Bain no. 253, North Lee no. 22], Brian North Lee [1984, Bain no. 259, North Lee no. 26], John D. N. Retallack [1974, Bain no. 232, North Lee no. 11], Benoît Junod [1983, Bain no. 256, North Lee no. 25], Jacob Rothschild [1973, Bain no. 215, North Lee no. 9], David J. Profumo [1984, Bain no. 363, North Lee no. 30], and Raymond & Pamela Lister [1984, Bain no. 262, North Lee no. 29]. Stapled soft binding. Shirley Smith's copy with his studio ex libris.
  - My Personal Bookplates. Published by Brian North Lee and Printed by Pardy & Son, Ltd., Ringwood, Hampshire, 2001., Lee, Brian North; Pp. [1] 2-32; 215 x 140 mm (Volume Moss. no 7)
    Illustrations of bookplates by Joan Hassall, Reynolds Stone, Leo Wyatt, Mark Severin, John Lawrence, Richard Shirley Smith [1984, Ex Libris for Brian North Lee, Bain no.259, North Lee no. 26], Roy Cooney, Hilary Paynter and others. Extra-illustrated with four bookplates tipped in. Stapled soft binding. Shelved together with 'The Bookplate Library of Brian North Lee,' Claude Cox Catalogue 178, Ipswich (Summer, 2007) offering 735 items.
  - Bookplates by Richard Shirley Smith. Printed and published by Simon Lawrence at his Fleece Press, Upper Denby, Huddersfield, 2005 [2006]., Lee, Brian North; Pp. [1-6] 7-101; 250 x 165 mm (Volume Moss no. 8)
    Colophon reads: 'There are 275 copies of this book, and it has been a pleasure to print some of the very best bookplates ever made. Of these, forty copies (thirty-two for sale) contain a chemise holding four proofs of drawn bookplates, signed by the artist. The paper is T. H. Saunders HP, the type Van Dijck set at Whittington by Peter Pugwash Sanderson, and the reproductions of the bookplates were printed by Smith Settle, who also bound the book.' This is one of the 32 copies with four drawn bookplates [North Lee nos. 36, 40, 43, 52] signed and dated by Shirley Smith. Quarter bound in tan book cloth, boards covered in wood-grain paper; the clamshell box is covered in matching cloth lined with wood-grain paper. Note to Roger W. Moss from Simon Lawrence, The Fleece Press, laid in. Booklet 'More Fleece Press Books for 2005' (printed in an edition limited to 1200 copies) also laid in.
    This lavish catalogue of Shirley Smith's bookplates produced through 2003 was one of North Lee's last publications; in it he assigned numbers to the bookplates that are used throughout this checklist. For Shirley Smith's bookplates created after 2003 the numbering sequence has been continued. See bookplate list (Section III).
  - Engelse grafici: Joan Hassall, Alan Reynolds Stone, Leo Wyatt, Richard Shirley Smith. Sint-Niklaas, Belgium: Internationaal Exlibriscentrum. Catalogue for an exhibition held March 4-April 9, 1978., Pp. [1-4] 5-48; 200 x 180 mm (Volume Moss no. 9)
    List of Shirley Smith engravings [nos. 213-272 in exhibition], photograph and 10 wood engravings are reproduced: Jacob Rothschild bookplate [1973, Bain no. 215, North Lee no. 9], John Retallack bookplate [1974, Bain no. 232, North Lee no. 11], 'Butterflies on Flower' [1971, Shelley, Bain no. 174], 'Portrait of Erasmus' [1965, Bain no. 82], 'Cove House for Giles FitzHerbert' [1973, Bain no. 230], 'Two Women' [1973, Chesterfield, Letters, Bain nos. 217-228], Memoirs of a London Doll [1967, Bain nos. 116-131], George Taylor bookplate [1974, Bain no. 233, North Lee no. 12], 'Grasshopper' [1971, Shelley, Bain no. 175]. Stapled soft binding. Invitation to exhibition laid in.
  - A History of British Wood Engraving. Tunbridge Wells, Kent: Midas Books, 1978., Garrett, Albert; Pp. [1-4] 5-407 [408]; 283 x 230 mm (Volume Moss no. 10)
    Set in monotype Plantin by South Bucks Typesetters, Ltd., Beaconsfield; printed and bound by R. J. Acford, Chichester, Sussex. Biography of Richard Shirley Smith on pp. 397-398 with reproductions of one engraving from Cupid's Progress, The Periodical on p. 308 [1970, Bain no. 163] and four engravings from Lord Chesterfield's Letters to His Son on p. 319 [1973, Bain nos. 217, 218, 226, 227]. Bound in gray book cloth with dust jacket.
  - Sixteen Contemporary Wood Engravers. A collection of wood engravings printed from the original blocks to accompany an exhibition. Newcastle, David Esslemont, 1982., Esslemont, David; Pp. [1-24]; 262 x 191 mm (Volume Moss no. 11)
    Foreword by Anthony Tuck and Dudley Wilson. 'This book was designed and printed by David Esslemont on a Columbian press. The edition consists of 250 copies on Zerkall mould-made paper. This copy is no. 126.' Signed by Esslemont. Each engraving is printed on a single page without text. Wood engravings by Leslie Benenson, Simon Brett, Clair Dalby, David Esslemont, Anne Jope, Simon King, John Lawrence, Angela Lemaire, Garrick Palmer, Hilary Paynter, Monica Poole, Peter Reddick, Michael Renton, Richard Shirley Smith [p. 14], George Tute and Sarah Van Niekerk. The colophon includes a printed ex libris for Dudley Wilson by Leo Wyatt as a tribute to the artist who had just died. Sewn soft binding. Prospectus laid in.
    Shirley Smith is here represented by his mildly erotic wood engraving 'Thais'. Bain assigns it no. 257 for its appearance in David Burnett's Vines (1984), although it clearly predates that printing. The exhibition which this collection of wood engravings accompanied was a tribute to the growing interest in wood engraving in the North East of England. It was a joint venture sponsored partly by the Durham Light Infantry Museum and Arts Centre and partly by Collingwood College in the University of Durham.
  - Wood Engravings: Richard Shirley Smith a selection, 1960 to 1977. Printed by David Chambers at Cuckoo Hill Press, 1983., Whistler, Laurence, 1912-2000; Pp. [i-ii] [1-6] 7-80; 255 x 173 mm (Volume Moss no. 12)
    Limited edition of 187 copies; seven copies printed on Hosho and 180 copies printed on Basingwerk Parchment of which this is copy no. 50 signed by Shirley Smith. Quarter bound in leather with gray buckram boards in gray buckram slipcase. Three cards announcing the publication laid in.
    This first retrospective of Shirley Smith's wood engravings is by Sir Laurence Whistler (1912-2000), the brother of Rex Whistler (1905-1944), who remarks, 'It needs only a glance through these pages to discover that here is an artist whose scope is not narrow. With equal skill he handles the charming simplicities of doll's house furniture, portraits, houses, food, insects, animals, flowers—and scenes of imagination. In the end it is the last-named that catches and holds the attention. He seems to have discovered his true gift while interpreting, or simply responding to, poetry.'
  - "Profile of an Artist: Richard Shirley Smith." The Bookplate Journal III (March, 1985), Chambers, David, 1930-; Pp. 42-43 (Volume Moss no. 13)
    Photograph and reproduction of the Timothy Harman bookplate [1962, Bain no. 33; North Lee no. 3].
  - "The Painter as Wood Engraver: Richard Shirley Smith and His Studio." The Green Book (Autumn, 1985)., Saunders, Linda; Pp. 4-8; 210 x 147 mm (Volume Moss no. 14)
    Reproductions include the Brian North Lee bookplate [1977, Bain no. 259] and five other engravings: two from The Poems of Percy Bysshe Shelley: 'Keats's Deathmask in Rome' [1971, Bain no. 167] and 'Shelley at Baths of Caracalla' [1971, Bain no. 165]; 'Portrait of Pépé' [1980, Bain no. 245]; 'Triumph of Death' [1985, Messer Pietro Mio, Bain no. 279]; and 'Two Fantastics' [1984, Bain no. 283]. Sewn soft binding. Prospectus for The Green Book illustrated with 'Two Fantastics' laid in.
  - A Catalogue of Fine Press Printers in the British Isles. Oxford: Inky Parrot Press, 1986., Colverson, Tom; Pp. [i-iv], [1-48], [49-50]; 205 x 210 mm (Volume Moss no. 15)
    Typeset by John Rose in 11-point Plantin on a CCRTronic phototypesetter, printed litho by Parchment (Oxford), Ltd., and bound by Paperback Binders (Oxford), Ltd. The text pages are printed on 140gsm Kaskad Pintail Cream and Kestrel Corn used for the endpapers. The cover is printed on 350gsm Kaskad Lapwing Brown from Robert Horne Paper Company, Ltd. Richard Shirley Smith's 'Cornucopias' [1985, Messer Pietro Mio, Bain no. 268] illustrates the paragraph describing Michael Mitchell's Libanus Press on page 27. Glued soft binding.
  - Second Conference of Fine Press Printing. November 22, 1986, Inky Parrot Press; Pp. [1-18]; 210 x 210 mm (Volume Moss no. 16)
    Conference program illustrated with wood engravings, including three by Richard Shirley Smith: 'Hands' [1985, Messer Pietro Mio, Bain no. 266], 'Girl's Head' [1984, Vines, Bain no. 258], 'Dark Tower' [1961, A Point of Departure, Bain no. 23]. Folded sheets.
  - Painting Murals: Images, Ideas and Techniques. London: Macdonald Orbis, Macdonld & Co. (Publishers), Ltd., 1987., Seligman, Patricia, 1950-; Pp. [1-8] 9-168; 260 x 260 mm (Volume Moss no. 17)
    Filmset by Bookworm Typesetting, printed and bound in Spain by Graficromo SA. Three murals by Richard Shirley Smith reproduced on pp. 63, 93 and 136.
    Like Caroline Cass's book on murals (no. 20 below), Patricia Seligman's Painting Murals was reissued in the United States in both hardback and paperback editions. Unfortunately she did not identify Shirley Smith's murals by name or location.
  - Engravers: A Handbook for the Nineties. Introduction by Simon Brett. Cambridge: Silent Books, 1987., Society of Wood Engravers; Pp. [1-7] 8-112; 243 x 172 mm (Volume Moss no. 18)
    Reproduces eight of Shirley Smith's wood engravings: 'Girl's Head' [1984, Vines, Bain no. 258], 'Head of Pan' [1971, Shelley, Bain no. 183], 'Altar' [1985, Messer Pietro Mio, Bain no. 267], 'Triumph of Death' [1985, Messer Pietro Mio, Bain no. 279], 'Decorative Rule' [1965, Folio Society, Bain no. 80], 'Wreathed Urn' [1971, Shelley, Bain no. 182], 'Heart Pendant' [1985, Messer Pietro Mio, Bain no. 281], and 'Rhinoceros Beetle' [1978, Buzz Buzz, Bain no. 151]. Perfect bound paperback.
  - Engravers: Two. A Handbook Compiled for the Society of Wood Engravers. Introduction by Simon Brett. Cambridge: Silent Books, 1992., Society of Wood Engravers; Pp. [1-7] 8-144; 243 x 172 mm (Volume Moss no. 19)
    Expanded edition of the above [no. 18] with the same Shirley Smith engravings reproduced. Perfect bound paperback.
  - Grand Illusions: Contemporary Interior Murals. Oxford: Phaidon Press, 1988., Cass, Caroline; Pp. [1-8] 9-160; 288 x 248 mm (Volume Moss no. 20)
    Shirley Smith's murals illustrated. 25, 38-39, 43, 61, 152. Bound in gray book cloth with dust jacket.
    Caroline Cass's survey of contemporary murals, like Patricia Seligman's book the year before (no.17 above), was published in both England and the United States in several hardback and paperback editions. Here Shirley Smith's trompe l'oeil murals, the first of which he executed in 1976 for owners of the Doric Villa in Regent's Park, were properly credited.
  - The Wood Engravings of Richard Shirley Smith. Cambridge: Silent Books, 1994., Shirley Smith, Richard; Pp. [i-iv] [1-6] 7-72 [73-76]; 280 x 203 mm (Volume Moss no. 21)
    Typeset by Libanus Press, Marlborough; printed at The Alden Press, Osney Mead, Oxford. Limited to one hundred copies of which this is no. 27 signed by Shirley Smith. Photograph and one hundred twenty wood engravings reproduced with two signed and numbered prints in a chemise: 'Temple of Antoninus & Faustina, Rome' [1961, Bain no. 8] and 'Angel Visits Anna and Joachim, Rome' [1961, Bain no. 6]. Bound in dark red book cloth with paper-covered boards printed with reproductions of Shirley Smith engravings. Dark red slip case.